Guide to the Howard Roberts Lamar Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Howard Roberts Lamar papers
1942-1993
WA MSS S-2639
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
48.62
(54 boxes) + 2 broadside folders, 68 film reels
The Howard Roberts Lamar papers document the research, writing, teaching, and administrative activities of Yale history professor Howard Lamar from the 1940s through 2000. Included in the papers are manuscript drafts of books, articles, speeches, and book reviews; lecture notes for the history courses he taught at Yale and other universities; topical and personal files; and correspondence. Project proposals, scripts, research material, production files, photographs, and films document the "Westering" film project which Lamar co-developed in the 1970s.
Lamar, Howard Roberts, 1923-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Yale University Press, 1957, and Howard Lamar Roberts, 1994, 2002, and 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Cold Storage 31-98 (film reels): Restricted fragile material. Consult the Beinecke Library Access Services department for additional information.
Boxes 20-21 and 109-119: Restricted until 2035. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 22: Restricted until 2064. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 120: Restricted until 2020. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Boxes 121-122: Restricted until 2075. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Access to original audio visual recordings is restricted pending reformatting. Consult the Beinecke Library Access Services department for additional information.
Box 123 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Copies of electronic files disks #4-21 from Box 99 are available through Access Services.
Box 124 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Howard Roberts Lamar, 1923-
Howard Roberts Lamar, historian of the trans-Mississippi West, was born in Tuskegee, Alabama in 1923. He received a B.A. from Emory University in 1944, and a Masters (1945) and Ph.d. (1951) in History from Yale University. He was an instructor at the University of Massachusetts and Wesleyan University between 1945 and 1949, and taught at Yale from 1949 to 1994. He held a number of administrative positions at Yale including chair of the Department of History 1962-1963 and 1967-1970, Dean of the College 1979-1985, and President of the University 1992-1993. He is Sterling Professor Emeritus of American History at Yale.
Scope and Contents
The Howard Roberts Lamar papers document the research, writing, teaching, and administrative activities of Yale history professor Howard Lamar from the 1940s through 2000. Included in the papers are manuscript drafts of books, articles, speeches, and book reviews; lecture notes for history courses he taught at Yale and other universities; topical and personal files; and correspondence. Project proposals, scripts, research material, production files, photographs, and films document the "Westering" film project which Lamar co-developed in the 1970s.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four groupings: I. February 1957 Acquisition, 1956. II. June 1994 Acquisition, 1942-1993. III. July 2002 Acquisition, 1969-1979. IV. August 2010 Acquisition, 1942-2000.
Educators; Historians; History -- Study and teaching -- United States; West (U.S.) -- History; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Motion pictures (visual works); Photographic prints; Sound recordings; Audiocassettes; Educators; Historians; Lamar, Howard Roberts, 1923-; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University. Department of History; Yale University -- Faculty
- February 1957 Acquisition, 1956; 1; 0.42; (1 box)
  General note
  Formerly classed as Uncat WA MS Lamar.
  - Dakota Territory, 1861-1889: A Study of Frontier Politics, typescript, 1956; 5 (Box 1)
- June 1994 Acquisition, 1942-1993; 2; 20.25; (22 boxes)
  Formerly classed as Uncat WA MS 177.
  Arrangement
  Arranged in five series: Writings, Lecture Notes, Topical Files, Personal Files, and Publications.
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of various typescripts of books, articles and papers, speeches, book reviews; files relating to professional projects; class and lecture notes from courses both studied and taught by Lamar; correspondence, and miscellaneous publications.
  - Writings, 1946-1991
    Includes manuscripts of books, articles and papers, speeches, and book reviews by Howard Lamar.
    - Books, 1955-1985
      - Dakota Territory, 1861-1889; a Study of Frontier Politics, typescript draft, 1955; 5 (Box 2)
      - The Far Southwest, 1846-1912: a Territorial History (Box 2)
        - Typescript drafts, 1965; 20 (Box 2)
        - Typescript drafts, 1965; 5 (Box 3)
        - Proofs, 1965 (Box 3)
        - Index, 1965; 2 (Box 3)
      - The Frontier in History: North America and Southern Africa Compared, 1981
        - Typescript drafts, circa 1980; 4 (Box 3)
        - Typescript drafts, circa 1980; 5 (Box 3)
        - Research and notes, circa 1980; 3 (Box 3)
      - Gold Seeker: Adventures of a Belgian Argonaut During the Gold Rush Years, by Jean-Nicolas Perlot; edited by Howard R. Lamar
        - Typescript drafts, circa 1985; 19 (Box 4)
        - Typescript drafts, circa 1985; 19 (Box 5)
        - Footnotes, circa1985 (Box 6)
        - Perlot correspondence, 1855-1866 (typescript copies), circa 1985 (Box 6)
        - Research and notes, 1978-1986; 4 (Box 6)
        - Bibliography, ca. 1985; 7 (Box 6)
      - "Jefferson, France, and Napoleon" (not published), drafts and outlines, undated; 3 (Box 6)
      - Odds and Ends; Or, Incidents of a Cruise in the Pacific in the U.S. Ship Portsmouth, by Fore Peak, Pseudonym for Joseph T. Downey, 1845-1848, typescript drafts, ca. 1958; 4 (Box 6)
        Edited by Howard Lamar and published as The Cruise of the Portsmouth, 1845-1847)
      - U.S. chapters for John W. Hall's world history volume, typescript drafts and notes, 1972; 4 (Box 6)
    - Articles and papers, 1946-1978
      - "Colorado: The Centennial State in the Bicentennial Year", 1976 (Box 7)
      - "The American Farm Bureau Federation", 1946; 6 (Box 7)
      - "Persistent Frontier: The West in the Twentieth Century", circa 1973; 2 (Box 7)
      - "Public Values and Private Dreams: South Dakota's Search for Identity, 1850-1900", 1978; 4 (Box 7)
    - Speeches, 1950-1989
      - Yale Speeches (Box 7)
        - Freshman Assembly addresses, 1955-1984; 10 (Box 7)
        - Yale Club and alumni talks, 1976-1989; 6 (Box 7)
        - Other, 1950-1990; 50 (Box 8)
      - Non-Yale speeches, 1962-1988; 24 (Box 8)
      - Non-Yale speeches, 1982-1988; 12 (Box 9)
    - Book reviews, 1951-1989; 46 (Box 9)
    - Book reviews, 1976-1989; 66 (Box 10)
  - Lecture notes, 1945-1980
    Includes outlines, notes, and other materials for classes Lamar taught at Yale and other universities.
    - Yale courses
      - "The New Freedom," first (guest) lecture at Yale, 1950 (Box 11)
      - Silliman seminar, 1957-1958 (Box 11)
      - History 20, 1950-1959; 23 (Box 11)
      - History 20, 1950-1956; 9 (Box 12)
      - History 37, 1950-1980; 17 (Box 12)
      - History 37, 1967-1976; 14 (Box 13)
      - History 180, 1962-1969; 15 (Box 13)
      - History 180, 1950-1969; 13 (Box 14)
      - History 186, 1955-1962; 3 (Box 14)
      - History 203, 1963; 3 (Box 14)
      - History 208a, 1972-1973; 2 (Box 14)
      - History 291, Comparative Frontiers, 1979; 20 (Box 15)
      - History, M.A. in Teaching (M.A.T.) program, Yale Summer Term, 1962; 5 (Box 15)
    - Non-Yale courses
      - Stanford Summer Term, 1969; 2 (Box 15)
      - History, U.S. Army Specialized Reserve Training Program, University of Massachusetts, 1945; 2 (Box 16)
      - European History, University of Massachusetts, 1946-1947; 7 (Box 16)
      - American History, Wesleyan University, 1948-1949; 7 (Box 16)
  - Topical Files, 1960-1993
    Includes reports, meeting minutes, and other material relating to Lamar's activities at Yale and other institutions.
    - American Council of Learned Societies, 1960-1962 (Box 17)
    - Bell, Wendell, 1983-1984 (Box 17)
    - Center for Southern Culture, 1975-78 (Box 17)
    - "Dwight Hall," by L. Freedman, 1983 (Box 17)
    - Far Southwest, 1966-1967 (Box 17)
    - Giamatti speeches, 1979-1985 (Box 17)
    - History Education Project, 1976-1977 (Box 17)
    - Humanities Review, 1973-1974 (Box 17)
    - Indian Forum, 1976 (Box 17)
    - Mississippi Valley Historical Association, 1963-1964 (Box 17)
    - Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, 1974-1975 (Box 17)
    - National Humanities Institute, 1974-1976 (Box 17)
    - Report on Graduate History Program, University of Montana, 1972 (Box 17)
    - Review of summer seminar, W.T. Jackson, 1975 (Box 17)
    - Reviews of books by Lamar, 1978-1993 (Box 17)
    - St. Paul's School, 1983 (Box 17)
    - Time-Life Books, "Western Classics", 1979 (Box 17)
    - Virginia Commonwealth University, 1979 (Box 17)
    - Yale University Council on Humanities (Box 17)
    - Yale University, Department of History, 2 (Box 17)
    - "Yale Today" questionnaire (Box 17)
  - Personal Files, 1942-1991
    Consists of notes, papers, and other material relating to Lamar's undergraduate studies at Emory University, a few calendars from his years as an administrator at Yale, and correspondence.
    - Undergraduate class notes, essays and related material.
      - English, 1942 (Box 18)
      - History, 15 (Box 18)
      - Philosophy, 1943; 2 (Box 18)
      - Time Magazine, 1945 Apr 23, May 7 (Box 18)
    - Calendars, 1979, 1990-1991; 2 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence
  - Printed Material
    Consists of books, periodicals, brochures, pamphlets, and offprints not written by Lamar.
    - Bennington College: In the Beginning, by Thomas P. Brockway, 1981 (Box 19)
    - Proceedings of the American Antiquarian Society, Vol. 87, Part 2, 1977 Oct (Box 19)
    - South Dakota History, Vol. 11, no. 4, 1981 (Box 19)
    - William Reece Co. sale catalogs (Box 19)
    - Yale Alumni Magazine, Vol. XLVII, no. 8, 1984 (Box 19)
    - Yale Daily News (various issues), 1979-1980 (Box 19)
    - Yale Weekly Bulletin and Calendar (various issues), 1979-80 (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous pamphlets, brochures, 1963-1987 (Box 19)
  - Restricted Material
    - Restricted correspondence (Box 20)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted until 2035. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
    - Restricted correspondence (Box 21)
    - Restricted correspondence (Box 22)
      Restricted until 2064. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
- July 2002 Acquisition, 1969-1979; 3; 5.67; (7 boxes) + 1 broadside folder, 68 film reels
  Formerly classed as Uncat MSS 403.
  Arranged by type of material.
  Consists of correspondence, project proposals, research files, scripts, film production files, photographs, films and other materials documenting the "Westering" film project.
  - "Westering" project proposals, 1976-77; 4 (Box 23)
  - Juan Bautista de Anza scripts, undated; 3 (Box 23)
  - Charles Siringo material
    - Research files, 10 (Box 23)
    - Siringo scripts, 1976 May-Jul, undated; 9 (Box 24)
    - Film production files
      - Scene list, 1977 (Box 24)
      - Director's sheets (Box 24)
      - Editing script, 1977 (Box 24)
      - Sound effects, 3 (Box 24)
      - Lined script and editor's log, 1976; 3 (Box 24)
      - Rough cue sheets (Box 24)
      - Film log, 2 (Box 25)
      - Film log, "blue binder", 2 (Box 25)
      - Interview transcripts, "Phil's Copy, Volume 1", 2 (Box 25)
      - Interview transcripts, "Phil's Copy, Volume 2", 2 (Box 25)
    - Production photographic documentation
      - Photographs, 1975-1979; 32 (Box 25)
      - Photographs, 3 (Box 26)
      - Polaroids, 3 (Box 26)
      - Slides, 3 (Box 26)
      - Negatives, 1979; 2 (Box 26)
      - Dailies, outtakes, work print, and answer print (16mm film) (Box 26)
  - Adolph Sutro material
    - Research files, 14 (Box 26)
    - Research files, 22 (Box 27)
    - Scripts, 1977; 2 (Box 28)
  - Printed material, 1970-1975
    - The American West, Vol. VII, no. 3; Vol. X, no. 1, 1970, 1973 (Box 28)
    - The Change of Officials in Tzo'ontahal, Chiapas, Mexico, by June Nash, preprinted from Publication 24 of Middle American Research Institute, 1970 (Box 28)
    - Frontier America: The Far West, exhibition catalog, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, 1975 (Box 28)
    - The Westerners, by Dee Brown, 1974 (Box 28)
  - Oversize
    - Westward to Promontory, by Barry B. Combs (from Charles Siringo research files), 1969 (Box 29)
    - Rough cue sheets (from Charles Siringo film production files) (Box 29)
    - Production photographs (from Charles Siringo production photographic documentation), 13 (Box 29)
    - Research file (from Adolph Sutro research files) (Box 29)
    - Director's sheets (from Charles Siringo production files) (Box 30 Broadside)
  - Restricted Fragile Material
    - Siringo dailies and outtakes, workprints and answer print (from Charles Siringo production photographic documentation)
      Access to this material is restricted pending reformatting. For more information consult the Beinecke Library Access Services department.
      - Dailies and outtakes 1 (Box 31)
      - Dailies and outtakes 2 (Box 32)
      - Dailies and outtakes 3 (Box 33)
      - Dailies and outtakes 4 (Box 34)
      - Dailies and outtakes 5 (Box 35)
      - Dailies and outtakes 6 (Box 36)
      - Dailies and outtakes 7 (Box 37)
      - Dailies and outtakes 8 (Box 38)
      - Dailies and outtakes 9 (Box 39)
      - Dailies and outtakes 10 (Box 40)
      - Dailies and outtakes 11 (Box 41)
      - Dailies and outtakes 12 (Box 42)
      - Dailies and outtakes 13 (Box 43)
      - Dailies and outtakes 14 (Box 44)
      - Dailies and outtakes 15 (Box 45)
      - Dailies and outtakes 16 (Box 46)
      - Dailies and outtakes 17 (Box 47)
      - Dailies and outtakes 18 (Box 48)
      - Dailies and outtakes 19 (Box 49)
      - Dailies and outtakes 20 (Box 50)
      - Dailies and outtakes 21 (Box 51)
      - Dailies and outtakes 22 (Box 52)
      - Dailies and outtakes 23 (Box 53)
      - Dailies and outtakes 24 (Box 54)
      - Dailies and outtakes 25 (Box 55)
      - Dailies and outtakes 26 (Box 56)
      - Dailies and outtakes 27 (Box 57)
      - Dailies and outtakes 28 (Box 58)
      - Dailies and outtakes 29 (Box 59)
      - Dailies and outtakes 30 (Box 60)
      - Dailies and outtakes 31 (Box 61)
      - Dailies and outtakes 32 (Box 62)
      - Dailies and outtakes 33 (Box 63)
      - Dailies and outtakes 34 (Box 64)
      - Dailies and outtakes 35 (Box 65)
      - Dailies and outtakes 36 (Box 66)
      - Dailies and outtakes 37 (Box 67)
      - Dailies and outtakes 38 (Box 68)
      - Dailies and outtakes 39 (Box 69)
      - Dailies and outtakes 40 (Box 70)
      - Dailies and outtakes 41 (Box 71)
      - Dailies and outtakes 42 (Box 72)
      - Dailies and outtakes 43 (Box 73)
      - Dailies and outtakes 44 (Box 74)
      - Dailies and outtakes 45 (Box 75)
      - Dailies and outtakes 46 (Box 76)
      - Dailies and outtakes 47 (Box 77)
      - Dailies and outtakes 48 (Box 78)
      - Dailies and outtakes 49 (Box 79)
      - Dailies and outtakes 50 (Box 80)
      - Dailies and outtakes 51 (Box 81)
      - Dailies and outtakes 52 (Box 82)
      - Dailies and outtakes 53 (Box 83)
      - Dailies and outtakes 54 (Box 84)
      - Dailies and outtakes 55 (Box 85)
      - Dailies and outtakes 56 (Box 86)
      - Dailies and outtakes 57 (Box 87)
      - Dailies and outtakes 58 (Box 88)
      - Dailies and outtakes 59 (Box 89)
      - Dailies and outtakes 60 (Box 90)
      - Dailies and outtakes 61 (Box 91)
      - Dailies and outtakes 62 (Box 92)
      - Dailies and outtakes 63 (Box 93)
      - Dailies and outtakes 64 (Box 94)
      - Dailies and outtakes 65 (Box 95)
      - Work prints 1 (Box 96)
      - Work prints 2 (Box 97)
      - Answer print (Box 98)
- August 2010 Acquisition, 1942-2000; Series IV; 22.27; (25 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
  Consists of writings, lecture notes, correspondence, computer disks, research, and personal files, and material relating to the Westering project.
  Box 124 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Writings, 1950-1995
    - Books
      - Cruise of the Portsmouth, edited by Howard Lamar, 1964 (Box 99)
      - "'The Soldier's Business is to Fight': The New Military History and the American Frontier" (not published), 1996 (Box 99)
      - "The American Discoverers" (proposal), undated (Box 99)
      - "The American Way: A Concise History of the United States" (prospectus), undated (Box 99)
    - Articles
      - "Historical Relevance and the American West", undated (Box 99)
      - Preface to Stella M. Drumm's edition of Down the Santa Fe Trail and into Mexico: the Diary of Susan Shelby Magoffin, 1846-184 7, 1962 (Box 99)
      - "Public Values and Private Dreams: South Dakota's Search for Identity, 1950-1900", 1975 (Box 99)
      - "Statehood for Utah: A Different Path", 1971 (Box 99)
      - "Trends in Western Historiography", undated (Box 99)
    - Editing projects
      - Readers Encyclopedia of the American West, circa 1987-1993; 7 (Box 99)
        Includes 10 3.5" and 8 5.25" computer disks.
        Existence and Location of Copies
        Copies of electronic files are available through Access Services: Disk #4-21.
    - Speeches
      - Yale Speeches
        - Freshman Assembly addresses, 1974-1992; 13 (Box 100)
        - Yale Club and alumni talks, 1981-1995; 9 (Box 100)
        - Miscellaneous Yale speeches, 1950-1994; 10 (Box 100)
      - Non-Yale Speeches, 29 (Box 100)
    - Recordings
      - Campaign Fifty-Six: Sounds of an Election Year, 1956; 2 (Box 100)
        Includes typescripts and printed brochure.
      - "The Mountain Men" in The American West: The Frontier Era, 1976; 1; 00:30:45 (Box 124, Item barcode 39002091397043)
        Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Lecture Notes, 1949-1995
    - Yale courses
      - History 20, circa 1949-1960; 25 (Box 101)
      - History 37, circa 1952-1977; 12 (Box 101)
      - History 37, circa 1966-1983; 36 (Box 102)
      - History 37, circa 1963-1978; 30 (Box 103)
      - History 140, 1986 (Box 103)
      - History 141, 1977 (Box 103)
      - History 180, circa 1955-1962; 3 (Box 103)
      - History 181, 1966 (Box 103)
      - History 186, circa 1955-1962; 2 (Box 103)
      - History 203, 1964; 3 (Box 103)
      - History 203, circa 1963-1976; 30 (Box 104)
      - History 266, circa 1952 (Box 104)
      - History 291, circa 1977-1981; 8 (Box 104)
      - History 296, 1973 (Box 104)
      - History 298, circa 1970-1976; 4 (Box 104)
      - History 298, circa1970-1978 (Box 105)
      - History 737, 1977-1987; 16 (Box 105)
    - Non-Yale courses
      - Western Art as Social and Environmental History, Summer Institute in Western American Studies, Buffalo Bill Historical Center, Cody, Wyoming, 1995; 10 (Box 105)
  - Personal Files, 1942-1994
    - Undergraduate class notes, essays and related material.
      - French, undated (Box 106)
      - History, 1942-1944; 9 (Box 106)
      - Political Science, 1944 (Box 106)
      - Class note cards, undated; 3 (Box 106)
    - Graduate school history papers, 1947, undated (Box 106)
    - Publications
      - Miscellaneous Yale and non-Yale brochures, pamphlets, magazine issues, 1945-1994 (Box 106)
      - Western History Association conference programs, 1964-1992; 5 (Box 106)
  - Research Files, 1956-1990
    - North American Indians, circa 1956-1987; 4 (Box 107)
    - Bibliographies, circa 1975-1990; 20 (Box 107)
  - Westering Files, 1976
    - Press coverage, 1976 (Box 107)
    - Bibliography, circa 1976; 2 (Box 107)
    - Juan Bautista de Anza material, circa 1976; 4 (Box 107)
    - Charles Siringo material, circa 1976 (Box 107)
    - Adolph Sutro material, circa 1976; 2 (Box 107)
  - Oversize Material, 1949, 1959
    - Reproduction of a map of "Part of the Continent of the United States" in four sheets, undated (Box 108 Broadside)
    - "Nevada Looks Ahead," a section of the Reno Evening Gazette, 1959 January 6 (Box 108 Broadside)
    - Life magazine, 1949 May 30 (Box 108 Broadside)
  - Restricted Material, circa 1952-2000
    Consists of general and topical correspondence files and correspondence from subseries above.
    - Restricted correspondence (Box 109)
      Includes general A-L correspondence
    - Restricted correspondence (Box 110)
      Includes general M-Z and topical file correspondence A-D
    - Restricted correspondence (Box 111)
      Includes topical file correspondence E-N
    - Restricted correspondence (Box 112)
      Includes topical file correspondence O-Western History Association (WHA), 1963
    - Restricted correspondence (Box 113)
      Includes topical file correspondence WHA, 1965-1993
    - Restricted correspondence (Box 114)
      Includes topical file correspondence WHA 1994-Y, and correspondence from Writings--Books; computer disk #22 stored in Restricted Fragile
    - Restricted correspondence (Box 115)
      Includes correspondence from Writings--Books and Writings--Articles; computer disks #1-3 stored in Restricted Fragile
    - Restricted correspondence (Box 116)
      Includes correspondence from Writings--Articles and Writings--Editing projects
    - Restricted correspondence (Box 117)
      Includes correspondence from Writings--Editing projects to Writings--Speeches
    - Restricted correspondence (Box 118)
      Includes correspondence from Writings--Speeches
    - Restricted correspondence (Box 119)
      Includes correspondence from Personal, Research, and Westering files
    - Restricted Dean's office records (Box 120)
    - Restricted student-related correspondence and records (Box 121)
      Restricted until 2075. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
    - Restricted student-related correspondence and records (Box 122)
  - Computer Media
    Electronic files: Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Computer disks from Box 99 (Box 123)
    - Computer disks from Box 114 (Box 123)
    - Computer disks from Box 115 (Box 123)